Preliminary Guide to the Benjamin Butterworth Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Benjamin Butterworth papers
1857-1908
1861-1898
MS 120
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(5 boxes)
Lawyer and politician. Scrapbooks of clippings and typed transcriptions of scrapbooks (1882-1898) concerning his career as lawyer, member of Congress from Ohio (1878-1882, 1886-1890) and commissioner of patents (1883-1885, 1897-1898). Included also are twenty letters which were originally part of the scrapbooks. Of these four are family correspondence (1857-1883) and the remainder are letters from political friends (1880-1898). The papers also contain the manuscript (typescript) introduction to The life of Major Benjamin Butterworth by Florence M. Bradford.
Butterworth, Benjamin, 1837-1898
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frank Butterworth in 1951.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Benjamin Butterworth Papers consist mainly of scrapbooks, and typed transcriptions of the scrapbooks, concerning the career of Benjamin Butterworth as lawyer, congressional representative (1878-82, 1885-90), and commissioner of patents (1883-85, 1898-98). Some of these scrapbooks originally contained a small number of letters as well as many newspaper clippings, but the letters have been removed and foldered separately. The other items in the Butterworth Papers are a scrapbook of clippings and family letters and a typescript introduction to The Life of Benjamin Butterworth.
The Butterworth papers were given to Yale University Library by Frank Butterworth in 1951. The typescripts were prepared by Florence M. Bradford.
Biographical / Historical
Admitted to the Ohio bar in 1861; served during the Civil War in the Union Army and later practiced law in Ohio; 1873-1875, state senator; 1875-1878, practiced law in Cincinnati; 1878, elected to the U.S. Congress, and reelected in 1880; 1883, appointed commissioner of patents; reelected to Congress in 1885, 1886, and 1892; 1892 opened law practice in Washington, D.C.; 1897 again became commissioner of patents.
Law; Patents; Middle West; Ohio -- Politics and government; United States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1900; United States -- Politics and government; Albums (Books); Lawyers; Politicians; Alverstone, Richard Everard Webster, Viscount, 1842-1915; Bradford, Florence M.; Bright, John, 1811-1889; Butterworth, Benjamin, 1837-1898; Butterworth, Elizabeth Linton; Carlisle, John Griffin, 1835-1910; Cartwright, Richard John, 1835-1912; Charlton, John, 1829-1910; Cortelyou, George B. (George Bruce), 1862-1940; Foster, Charles, 1828-1904; Grosvenor, Charles Henry, 1833-1917; Hanna, Marcus Alonzo, 1837-1904; Linton, Nathan, 1778-1858; McKinley, William, 1843-1901; Myers, Elizabeth Ann Davis; Proctor, Redfield, 1831-1908; Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906; Seiler, J. F.; Smith, Goldwin, 1823-1910; Smith, Richard, 1802-1878; Welles, Gideon, 1802-1878; Whitfield, S. A.
- Inventory
  - Elisabeth (Linton) Butterworth Scrapbook containing the following letters:
    - Butterworth, Benjamin (1837-1898), to his mother, 1881 August 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Linton, Nathan (1778-1858), to his daughter, Elizabeth (Linton) Butterworth, 1857 December 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Linton, Nathan [nephew?], to one of the sons of Nathan above, 1858 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Myers, Elizabeth Ann (Davis?), to her "uncle and father", 1877 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters removed from Benjamin Butterworth scrapbook as follows:
    - Alverstone, Richard Everard Webster, viscount, (1842-1915), to Butterworth, 1891 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bright, John (1811-1889), to Butterworth, 1885 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Butterworth, Benjamin (1837-1898), carbon copies of 15 letters to various persons, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Carlisle, John Griffin (1835-1910), to Butterworth, 1891 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Cartwright, Richard John Sir (1835-1912), to Erastus Wiman, 1889 December 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Carlton, John (1829-1910), to Butterworth, 1889 February 11, April 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Cortelyou, George Bruce (1862-), for President McKinley to Mr. & Mrs. Butterworth, 1897 September 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Foster, Charles (1828-1904), to Butterworth, 1880 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Grosvenor, Charles Henry (1833-), to H.R. Probasco, 1890 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hanna, Marcus Alonzo (1837-1904), to Butterworth, 1889 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Proctor, Redfield (1831-1908), to Butterworth, 1891 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Schurz, Carl (1829-1906), to Butterworth, 1891 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Seiler, J.F., to Butterworth, 1889 February (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Smith, Goldwin (1823-1910), to Butterworth. Marked "Printed.", 1893 April 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Smith, Richard, to Butterworth, 1891 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Welles, Gideon (1802-1878), to or about Capt. Cicero Price, 1864 April 26, December 22, 1865 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Whitfield, S.A. To Butterworth, 1890 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Telegrams on the death of Benjamin Butterworth, from various persons, including President McKinley (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Introduction of The Life of Major Benjamin Butterworth, typescript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of clippings, 1883-1886 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 6)
  - Typescript of clippings, 1887-1898 (Box 2, Folder 7 - 18)
  - Typescript of clippings, 1900-1908 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Typescript of clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Typescript of excerpts from scrapbooks, 1884-1890 May (Box 3, Folder 21 - 23)
  - Typescript of excerpts from scrapbooks, 1897 June-November (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Typescript of excerpts from scrapbooks, 1898-1908 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Scrapbook, 1861-1878 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Scrapbook, 1882-1896 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Scrapbooks, 1885-1887, 1892-1895 (Box 5, Folder 28)